Guide to the Irrigated Agriculture Research and Experiment Center (Prosser) Grapes/Wine Research Records 1940-1984
Washington State University Libraries Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections
Irrigated Agriculture Research and Experiment Center (Prosser) Grapes/Wine Research Records
1940-1984
Washington State University Libraries, Manuscripts, Archives and Special Collections
Archives 214
Washington State University. Irrigated Agriculture Research and Extension Center.
4.6 Linear feet of shelf space 4 Boxes
Consists of correspondence, memoranda, reports, test and research data, chiefly that assembled as working papers by Walter Clore and his associates.
Grapes have been a commercial crop in Washington since the late 19th century, with production concentrated in Yakima and Benton Counties. The Agricultural Experiment Station at Prosser first worked with grapes in the 1930s, and began work with wine and wine grape production in 1965. Much of the post-1965 effort was directed by Walter Clore.
Historical essays about grapes, wine and related experimentation in Washington can be found among these records, folders 237 and 238 in Box 4.
Records consist of correspondence, memoranda, reports, test and research data, chiefly that assembled as working papers by Walter Clore and his associates.
The filing arrangement is that which was in place when the records were received at the Libraries. This system was informal. The records were maintained as four alphabetical series of subject folders. These four divisions were not named or labeled individually; this filing system was apparent only because of distinct alphabetical sequences could be found in the records. Hence, the Libraries' staff is uncertain of the original themes of organization. Appearances suggest that the first series is concerned with administrative matters. The second and third series deal with tests and studies, some in laboratories and some in field tests, including various data collection efforts. The last series concerns matters other than the major grape and wine projects, such as strawberry and red currant projects. Because of the repetitive occurrences, users are advised to broaden any inquiry over all four series.
This collection is open and available for research use.
Records of the grape and wine projects of the Irrigated Agriculture Research and Experiment Center in Prosser were forwarded to the Washington State University Libraries in 1989 by Raymond Folwell of Department of Agricultural Economics (Archives accession number UA89-37).
Charles W. Nagel Papers, 1964-1991 (Cage 639)
Walter Clore Papers, 1961-1999 (Cage 668)
Charles W. Nagel Oral History Interview, 2005 (Cage 761)
Irrigation Branch Experiment Station (Prosser) Reports, 1919-1960 (Archives 76)
Irrigation Branch Experiment Station Records, 1910-1979 (Archives 200)
Irrigated Agriculture Research and Extension Center Photographs, 1919-1969 (PC 195)
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Clore, W. J.; Folwell, Raymond J.
Washington State University. Irrigated Agriculture Research and Extension Center -- Records and correspondence.; Washington State University. Irrigation Branch Experiment Station -- Records and correspondence.; State College of Washington. Irrigation Branch Experiment Station -- Records and correspondence.; Washington State University. Irrigation Branch Experiment Station.; State College of Washington. Irrigation Branch Experiment Station.
Fruit-culture -- Research -- Washington (State); Grapes -- Irrigation -- Washington (State); Irrigation farming -- Washington (State)
Agriculture; Washington (State)
- Series 1: Administration-related files
  - Agricultural Research Technologist, Ann Smith, 1979-1983 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Annual Report, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Budget - Grapes IAREC, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Budget, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Clark, Walter - Vancouver, WA, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Completed File, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Concord Yield Decline, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Conductivity Tests, Grapes, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Employee Records (Confidential), 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Federal Crop Insurance for Grapes, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Grape Certification Committee, 1968-1971 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Grape Reports, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Grapes, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Grapes, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Grapes - Crop Production, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Grapes, Planting at Dallesport, 1969-1974 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Henderson, Charles, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Purchase Orders - Wine Grapes, 1980-1984 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Prior Planting, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Productions, Wine Making, and Marketing of Wine Grapes in Washington, Project 0050, 1972-1979 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Project 0050 - Wine Grapes in Washington, 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Publications - Grapes Manuscript and Reprints, Clore and Brummund, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Releases to Certified Grape Growers, 1968-1976 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Sauer, Mike -- Cooperation, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Site Study Soil Analysis, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Snake River Vineyards 1975 data (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Snake River Vineyard Grapes, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Steele, Ted, 1973-1977 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Supply orders, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Survey of Vineyards, Frank Anderson (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Symptoms of Grape Disorders, 1976-1979 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Tri-State-Oregon's Proposals, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Tri-State Project, 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Tri-State Proposals for Idaho, 1979-1982 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Tri-State Wine, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Tri-State Wine Grape Demonstration Project, 1976-1979 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Tri-State Wine Grape Final Proposal, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Tri-State Wine Grape Project, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Tri-State Wine Project, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Wahluke Slope Plantings, 1967-1968, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Washington Water Research Center, 1979-1981 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - WEMIS, 1980-1983 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Winter Injury Report, 1955-1956 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Publications (working documents and drafts)
    - "The Effect of the December 1964 Freeze on Grapes," by Walter J. Clore and Vern P. Brummond (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - "Seasonal Changes in Low Temperature Resistance of Grape Buds," by E. L. Proebsting, M. Amhedullah, and V. P. Brummond, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Tri-State Wine Grape Demonstration Project Termination Report (Project 4485) (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Washington State Concord Grape Research Council, Cultural Studies of Concord Grapes, Reports, 1961-1978 (Box 1, Folder 47)
- Series 2: Studies, tests and data I
  - Accumulated Heat Units - From end of test to 6/15 inc, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Black Leaf - Trenching trial - Brulotte, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Blodgett, Earle - Planting, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Campbell Early Growers (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Cold Hardiness, 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Concord Grape Maturity: S.S., T.A., color, pH, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Correspondence, 1960-1970 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - CRO (Columbia River Orchards) Rock Island Dam Area, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Divron (Karmox) Injury, H-6 Concords, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Dying Arm Diseased Vineyard - Vine location, 1974-1976 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Dying Arm Reprints, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Etherel Concentrations, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Ethepion Treatments B-1, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Foundation Block Indexing, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Foundation Block Indexing, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Foundation Block Planting and Index Record, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Foundation Block Releases, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Foundation Block Releases, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Foundation Block Materials for Indexing, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Foundation Materials Released, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - French Hybrids (Amphographic), 1971 (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - Frost Injury from Sprinkler Irrigation, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - Frost Injury to Grape References, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - Grafting Propagation (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - Grape -- Coop and Growers, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 72)
  - Grapes II acid-ASH, 1958-1959 (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - Grape Buds -- Critical Temperatures (Box 2, Folder 74)
  - Grape Composition Studies -- Inner Pulp vs. Skin Data, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 75)
  - Grape Cutting Material Available from Sidney, B.C., 1977 (Box 2, Folder 76)
  - Grape Cuttings -- Rooting of Time and Temperature, 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 77)
  - Grape Data by Variety and Color, 1968-1969 (Box 2, Folder 78)
  - Grape Juice I Sugar-ss-Brix, 1956-1959 (Box 2, Folder 79)
  - Grape Juice -- Processing Data, Graphs, Tables, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 80)
  - Grape Soil -- Plant-Fruit Study (Box 2, Folder 81)
  - Grape Variety Cooperators Established in, 1973, 1970-1975 (Box 2, Folder 82)
  - Grapes Variety Data, 1949-1965 (Box 2, Folder 83)
  - Grape Varieties Maturity Studies, 1959-1962 (Box 2, Folder 84)
  - Grape Harvest, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 85)
  - Grape -- Talks, 1961, 1965-1968 (Box 2, Folder 86)
  - Hardiness Research -- Proebsting, 1976-1977 (Box 2, Folder 87)
  - Heat Units, 1943-1964 (Box 2, Folder 88)
  - Heat Units, 1955-1964 (Box 2, Folder 89)
  - Heat Units, 1963-1978 (Box 2, Folder 90)
  - Heat Units, 1968-1969 (Box 2, Folder 91)
  - Heat Units, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 92)
  - Heat Units, 1971-1973 (Box 2, Folder 93)
  - Heat Units, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 94)
  - Heat Units -- McNary Dam (Box 2, Folder 95)
  - Herbicides -- 2-4-D Contamination, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 96)
  - Hi-pH, Hi-T.A. Wine Grapes, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 97)
  - Hogue Fertility Studies, 1972-1975 (Box 2, Folder 98)
  - Hogue Vineyard 2-4-D Contamination, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 99)
  - Insecticide Data Cone, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 100)
  - Job Description Reprint, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 101)
  - Leaf Removal -- Simulated 2-4-D and Conforminated Leaves Opposite Cluster. 1974-Taggares Block 5 RIO and II, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 102)
  - Light, X. Wm. and Green, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 103)
  - Low Temperature Research -- Proebsting and Brummund (Box 2, Folder 104)
  - Manuscripts (Box 2, Folder 105)
  - Metrological Data -- Roza, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 106)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 107)
  - National Grape Sheets, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 108)
  - Niagara -- Maturation Study, 1977, 1977-1978 (Box 2, Folder 109)
  - Nursery Grown Plant by Year, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 110)
  - Phenological Data -- Grapes, 1975, 76, 77 (Box 2, Folder 111)
  - Planting Plan -- Holland Farm, Wahluke Slope, 1970-1973 (Box 2, Folder 112)
  - Project Report 1628. Cultural --Concord Grapes, 1972-1975 (Box 2, Folder 113)
  - Racurg Treatments, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 114)
  - Registered Materials, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 115)
  - Research Projects Proposed (Box 2, Folder 116)
  - Roza Vineyard Yield, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 117)
  - Soil Analysis Reports -- Vineyards, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 118)
  - Soil Moisture in Percentage by Volume by Neutron Scatter, 1968-1969 (Box 2, Folder 119)
  - Soil Test Interpretations (Box 2, Folder 120)
  - Spooner Vineyard, Rothrod Rd., 1975 (Box 2, Folder 121)
  - Statistical Evaluation Formulas (Box 2, Folder 122)
  - Studio Information, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 123)
  - Temperature Records, Maryhill, WA, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 124)
  - Varietal Wine Sales -- Liquor Control Board, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 125)
  - 1925 Variety Vineyard and Roza Yields, 1965-1966 (Box 2, Folder 126)
  - Variety Vineyard Data, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 127)
  - Washington State Grape Production Data, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 128)
  - Weather Data -- Temperature, Moses Lake, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 129)
  - Wine Grape Acreage Washington, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 130)
  - Wine Grape Sales, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 131)
  - Wine Grape Vineyard Data, 1967-1970 (Box 2, Folder 132)
  - Wine Regulations, Federal (Box 2, Folder 133)
  - Winery Supplies and Equipment, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 134)
  - Wing, Robert N., 1973-1978 (Box 2, Folder 135)
  - Wynne, Tom, 1972-1974 (Box 2, Folder 136)
- Series 3: Studies, Tests and Data II
  - Blossom Dates, Variety Vineyard, 1864 (Box 2, Folder 137)
  - Bud Damage, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 138)
  - Cold Hardiness -- Bracteatum, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 139)
  - Cold Hardiness -- by Time of Pruning, 1978-1979 (Box 2, Folder 140)
  - Cold Hardiness Chemical Treatment, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 141)
  - Cold Hardiness Manuscript, 1975-1976 (Box 2, Folder 142)
  - Cold Injury, 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 143)
  - Copper Deficiency in Grapes, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 144)
  - Correspondence I, 1973-1979 (Box 2, Folder 145)
  - Correspondence II, 1975-1979 (Box 2, Folder 146)
  - Critical Temperature for Concord Grapes, Pheno. Development, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 147)
  - Crown Gall Control Recommendation, 1975-1977 (Box 3, Folder 148)
  - Cutworm Control Manuscript (Box 3, Folder 149)
  - Dicamba on Concord Grapes, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 150)
  - Disease: Pierces -- Grape Vines (Box 3, Folder 151)
  - Drip Irrigation Study, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 152)
  - Electron Microscope, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 153)
  - E.P.A. -- 2-4-D Studies, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 154)
  - Ethephon (Studies), 1974 (Box 3, Folder 155)
  - Ethephon -- Taggares \# 9, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 156)
  - Ethephon (Studies), 1975 (Box 3, Folder 157)
  - Ethephon -- Hague Vineyard, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 158)
  - Ethephon -- Pinot Noir H-9, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 159)
  - Fe Sprays -- Soil Tests for N-Delayed and Normal Vineyards, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 160)
  - Fertilizer Plots: Hogue Vieyard-Dow, 1974-1975 (Box 3, Folder 161)
  - Fertilizer Recommendations -- Grapes, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 162)
  - Four Corners Grape Development Project (Box 3, Folder 163)
  - Freeze-Dryer, Instruction (Box 3, Folder 164)
  - Frost Injury -- Recovery, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 165)
  - Grapes: Declining Yields -- Concords (Box 3, Folder 166)
  - Grapes: Declining Yields -- National Survey Form (Box 3, Folder 167)
  - Grapes: Harvesters (Box 3, Folder 168)
  - Grapes: Miscell., 1968 (Box 3, Folder 169)
  - Grapes: Variety Studies: S.S. T.A. pH and Yield; Gibberellin Treatments, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 170)
  - Grapes: Vinifera -- Winter Injury, 1964-1965 (Box 3, Folder 171)
  - Grape Cuttings, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 172)
  - Grape Diseases - for Extra Mimeo (Box 3, Folder 173)
  - Grape Introduction from 1/1/1979 (Box 3, Folder 174)
  - Grape Juice Bulletin -- Mss (Box 3, Folder 175)
  - Grape Leaf Moisture 4, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 176)
  - Grape Plants Sent out, 1960-1961 (Box 3, Folder 177)
  - Grape Pressure Tests Durometer Readings, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 178)
  - Grape Prices: Cash Buyers, 1971-1977 (Box 3, Folder 179)
  - Grape Prices: California Statistics, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 180)
  - Grape Problems -- Concord (Box 3, Folder 181)
  - Grape Project -- Proposed Research, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 182)
  - Grape Rootstocks, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 183)
  - Grape Statistics -- California, Wines and Vines, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 184)
  - Grape Studies -- Conductivity, Pete Christiansen, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 185)
  - Grapevine Notes, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 186)
  - Grapevine Certification Regulations -- California, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 187)
  - Grapevine Fruitfulness Climatic Factors, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 188)
  - Growth Controlling Substances, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 189)
  - Growth Regulator Sprays, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 190)
  - H-9 Data, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 191)
  - Herbicide Labels (Box 3, Folder 192)
  - Maps -- Wahluke Slope (Box 3, Folder 193)
  - Maturity, Grapes for Wine (Box 3, Folder 194)
  - Phylloxera Survey, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 195)
  - Propagation -- Grapes, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 196)
  - Roza Vineyard Data, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 197)
  - Snake River Vineyards Data, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 198)
  - Temperature: Snake River Vineyards (Universal Lampco) (Box 3, Folder 199)
  - Temperature Records -- Patterson, Prosser, Trier, Germany (Box 3, Folder 200)
  - Tissue Analysis, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 201)
  - Trial Plantings, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 202)
  - Tri-State Wine Project, 1974-1978 (Box 3, Folder 203)
  - Tri-State Wine Grape Research, 1977-1978 (Box 3, Folder 204)
  - Weather Data -- Vinifera, 1960-1966 (Box 3, Folder 205)
  - Wine -- Yeast Source, 1964-1965, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 206)
  - Wine Analysis -- Vintage, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 207)
  - Weather Summary -- Germany, 1965-1966 (Box 3, Folder 208)
  - Wine and Must Analysis, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 209)
  - Wine and Must Analysis, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 210)
  - Wine Grape Acreage, 1966, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 211)
  - Wine Grape Acreage -- California, 1967-1968 (Box 3, Folder 212)
  - Wine Grape Data -- Wine Analysis, Taste Panel Results, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 213)
  - Wine Grape Data. Grapes for Wine: Maturity, Wine Tasting Panel Results, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 214)
  - Wine Grape Vineyard Data, Grapes for Wine Data, Wine Analysis. Tasting Panel Results, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 215)
  - Wine Samplings and Tastings, 1964-1965 (Box 3, Folder 216)
  - Winter Injury -- Varietal Response, 1968-1969 (Box 3, Folder 217)
  - Wine Grape Varieties -- Virus Free, Chemical Analysis, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 218)
  - Unlabeled, unidentified, undated, 1962(?) (Box 3, Folder 219)
- Series 4: Other files
  - Currants, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 220)
  - EDA Report, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 221)
  - Equipment, 1951, 1966, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 222)
  - Elderberries, 1957-1959 (Box 3, Folder 223)
  - Grape Quarantine Hearings, 1943, 1969-1976 (Box 3, Folder 224)
  - Processing, 1944-1949, 1957-1958 (Box 3, Folder 225)
  - Red Currants, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 226)
  - Rootstock Studies, 1944-1953 (Box 3, Folder 227)
  - Small Fruit Varieties for Western Washington, 1940-1965 (Box 3, Folder 228)
  - Strawberry Trials, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 229)
  - Strawberry Yields, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 230)
  - Strawberries, 1948-4-, 1958-61 (Box 3, Folder 231)
  - Strawberries Original Data, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 232)
  - Virus-free Stocks and Introduction, 1960-1962, 1965-1975 (Box 4, Folder 233)
  - Weather Data (Box 4, Folder 234)
  - Weather Data (Box 4, Folder 235)
  - Washington State Wine History for Raymond Folwell. Duplicates from Walter Clore, 1940-1965 (Box 4, Folder 236)
  - Washington State Wine History for Raymond Folwell. Duplicates from Walter Clore, 1966-1989 (Box 4, Folder 237)